So great guys, welcome, welcome, welcome to another
"Token 24/9" Dubai, thank you very much, Andrew Work.
It's definitely the best MC in the market.
Great, you guys are very lucky to have him today.
This episode is powered by Zappel Bank.
Experience the future of banking with Zappel Bank,
the first fully licensed
and regulated Bitcoin enabled banking group.
With Zappel Bank's all in one app,
you can grow, transact and secure your Bitcoin.
Earn annual Bitcoin yield paid daily
on your Bitcoin and US dollar savings
plus cashback on your card spending.
Or instantly send and receive Bitcoin
with the lighting network
and seamlessly transact in USDC, USDT, US dollars,
euros and pounds.
All this is backed by rock solid security,
including military-grade Swiss bunkers,
cutting edge digital protocols
and strict regulatory oversight.
Sign up now at zappobank.com/capsule
or check the link in the episode description.
This episode is brought to you by ACX Compliance,
your one stop shop for all your crypto compliance needs
in the UAE and beyond.
From Vara licensing support
to crypto compliance training and customized support,
including crypto specialized transaction monitoring
and SAR reporting filing support.
ACX Compliance has over 200 crypto compliance professionals
that are 100% training crypto
and 100% focused on the crypto industry.
If you're looking for a one stop shop
to really help you with all your crypto compliance needs,
think ACX Compliance.
Find out more at www.accompliance.com.
- Guys, we're gonna have a really fun time this morning.
Really talk about what's happening on the ETF flows,
what's happening on the institutional side.
And my goal today is very, very simple.
It's to share with you the latest color
and market intelligence we have
and then let you make your own decision
on what impact could be not on your business
but also on you personally as well as we look into the space.
And to do this, we have the dream team today.
As was mentioned, we have the Giovanni.
We have, actually, let me start from that side.
We have Evgeni Gyborg, who's obviously the founder
and CEO Wintermute.
One thing you may not know, but Evgeni,
he's a war hammer fan for all those of you in the space.
Evgeni, good to have you with us.
Of course, then we have Roger Baystone
from Frankl Templeton, who's the head of Ditch Lasset.
Interesting fun fact about him.
He's getting married in a couple of weeks
and he's here with us in Dubai.
(audience applauds)
And last but not least, Giovanni Visioso,
he's the executive director
of equity and alternative products.
And one fun fact about him,
he used to be a division one fencer in the U.S.
And that's something I used to be a fence as well
back in my day.
So maybe as after activity, we should do a little about.
So guys, we have a lot of topics to cover today,
especially on the ETF side, on the institutional flow as well.
But really, let's start with the ETF side.
Roger, I'm gonna start with you.
Frankl Templeton was obviously very involved
in the Bitcoin ETF approval in the U.S. in the process there.
Were you guys surprised by the flow
that we have seen in the Bitcoin side, on the ETF side?
And what is a type of investor you're seeing
who's coming into these ETF products?
We were pleasantly surprised
about the tremendous outcome of the, and success.
I mean, look, ETFs have been around
for a couple of decades now, really.
And it was the biggest launch,
the most successful launch in ETF history.
And you just can't walk away from that massive event.
I think it's gonna be shifting the nature
of all asset managers when they realized
that there is demand, not just institutional demand,
but up a wealth platforms and investment advisors
and individuals, quite frankly.
I think that's what we're seeing.
We're seeing a lot of different investors
coming into the spot Bitcoin ETFs in the U.S.
- It's interesting.
I think many people don't realize
that it was the most successful ETF launch in history.
I mean, at the fastest one even for one of the other ones
to hit $10 billion in assets,
which is quite incredible of that.
What was the impact on the futures market?
I know at CME, you guys have the Bitcoin futures.
What impact have you seen the ETF launch had
on the futures market?
- Now, it's been a tremendous impact.
And I think, you know, Roger, to your point, right?
I think that the marketplace anticipated
that the spot ETF in the U.S. would be successful.
But I don't think that the market anticipated
that it would be as successful, right?
But certainly what we've noticed, you know,
historically is that futures do tend to move first.
You know, the first ETF was the S&P Spider ETF,
which launched, you know, in 1997, I believe.
But that was 11 years after the first S&P
futures contracts launched.
You know, we saw like gold futures or ETFs launched
about 30 years after, say, futures existed.
So futures tend to move first.
And we certainly, you know, have been waiting for Bitcoin ETFs
to launch, you know, when we first introduced Bitcoin futures
in December 2017, we always had in the back of our minds
that futures would be, that ETFs would be a natural progression.
It took a little bit longer than anticipated.
I mean, the first ETF was a futures-based Bitcoin ETF,
was the ProShares futures-based ETF in the fall of 2021.
And that product had at the time was the most successful, right?
And really was dwarfed by the recent launch
of the spot Bitcoin ETFs in the US.
And what we've seen in terms of volume is that, you know,
last year on Bitcoin futures, we averaged about 1.6 billion
per day.
In March, we averaged over $6 billion per day.
And a lot of that is a result of liquidity providers,
for example, using our futures to hedge activity on the ETFs.
In fact, six out of the 10 new ETFs are benchmarked
to the CME and crypto facilities Bitcoin reference rate in New York.
That's a reference rate that publishes at 4 p.m. New York time.
And it coincides on with the NAB calculation
for a lot of these ETFs.
So we're seeing market participants leverage some
of our mechanisms, such as BTIC, basis-traded index clues,
which allows market participants that ability
to trade the futures contract relative to that net asset
value calculation print at 4 p.m. New York.
In fact, now in that 3 to 4 p.m. New York window,
we're averaging over $1 billion in that hour alone.
Whereas last year, as I mentioned,
we averaged $1.6 billion for the year.
So we've really seen tremendous success.
And I think that both products will grow together.
I think March, collectively, the ETFs traded over $110 billion.
The futures traded over $130 billion, so about 20% more.
But across other markets, we tend to see
that futures trade more than the ETFs.
But the futures are the base for helping the ETFs grow.
But it's really a symbiotic relationship.
And as the ETFs grow, so will the futures and vice versa.
Yeah, but I mean, I think it's normal that even
in traditional markets, right, the volumes of ETFs.
But I mean, and I want to get a review of this, Evgeny,
but on this point you mentioned, I mean, it's a bit ironic
that you're talking about in a 4 p.m. cut-off in crypto
of an asset that is 24/7.
And of course, we have the perpetual swap market in crypto,
which obviously is 24/7.
Yes, there's every eight-hour funding mechanism in place.
But when you look at the CME type of futures,
five years down the line, how do you
see that comparing to the whole perpetual swap,
crypto-derivative market, which obviously also
trades a couple of billion dollars a day?
No, it's interesting.
Certainly, the perpetual swaps, we're an innovation
in the industry, I think.
BitMax was the first to introduce such a product.
But I think that you really have different use cases
for perpetual swaps and futures, right?
I'd say that the perpetual swap product
is perhaps a little bit more retail-focused,
where we tend to see in our markets,
it's a regulated market, first of all.
We do tend to see more institutional flow in our space.
But when you look at the perpetual swap,
as you mentioned, Henry, there's the financing
that's every eight hours.
And that creates uncertainty.
Because if you consider a proprietary firm that's
providing liquidity, they don't know
what that fixing is going to be in the next eight hours.
So they're kind of like running their own models,
trying to guess what that financing is.
When you consider a future to contract,
there is a known end date.
So for anybody providing liquidity,
they know, for example, what the financing is
to the end date of that particular futures contract, right?
If you look at that implied financing,
like recently, just after the launch of the spot ETFs,
implied financing on some of the perpetuals
was annualized about 60%.
Now, if you think about anybody who's looking
to get exposure through that product,
at 60% annualized financing, that's really expensive.
So I think, you know, the use case for those products
is not, say, a hobbler, for example.
But I think it's really somebody who's looking to benefit,
perhaps from the leverage, and really looking to speculate
and hoping to, you know, to hit, do well, say,
with that leverage that's offered.
- But what, again, on this point,
what's your view on it?
Obviously, you guys are OTC broker,
you're market-making, you're providing liquidity
on, I presume, crypto derivatives as well.
What's your view on the future of the CME futures
versus the whole perpetual swap market,
especially that we're having a lot of the firms
are issuing these perps who are probably
gonna be regulated over the next couple of months and years.
- Yeah, look, I mean, there are pros and cons
to both products, and it's correct that, yeah,
retail is much more in the perps,
and institutional clients do prefer futures,
primarily because, yeah, there is a much greater
predictability of funding due to the effectively pay,
but there are features of swap, which are, yeah,
quite nice, like Xenobex buy, and yeah, in my previous life,
I was trying a lot of futures until CME,
and it's a fun process to roll them over every three months,
but it's, yeah, it's a bit annoying.
And so, yeah, that's a feature of perpetual swaps,
which is, yes, superior, to a big degree,
but yeah, the funding on predictability, yeah,
we'll see whether it will win hearts
of institutional people in the end or not.
I don't have a strong opinion on this.
- How do you even see the crippled derivative space
of all, do you think it's gonna change radically
over the next couple of years?
- I want to believe that some features
of the crypto market will be adopted,
namely, yeah, 24/7 trading would be really nice to see,
because that's, yeah, for us, crypto native people,
it's very weird that exchange is closed and open.
- Yeah.
- So I think that that will be a pretty important feature
for a lot of people, and yeah, I wonder when we will see it.
- Yeah, maybe it's a question more for you.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, like, what's your view on that?
- I mean, yeah, so look, you know,
our products are available to trade Sunday evening,
6 p.m. New York, to Friday evening, 5 p.m. New York.
So effectively, 23 hours a day,
and we have a one-hour break for me,
and it's between five and six every day.
But to your beginning's point, right,
crypto is a 24/7 market.
Now, we offer futures, we offer options on futures.
So we're noticing with our options products,
and we have daily, weekly options.
So what we're noticing is a lot of market participants now
trading our Monday expiring options contract
to sort of like hedge some of that weekend risk.
But I think longer term, it would be who, you know,
in exchange like CME to consider exploring, you know,
opening our market 24/7.
But in our case, you know, we're not just a crypto exchange.
We cover six other major asset classes.
So when we look to make a move like that,
you know, we have to consider the impacts
across these other six asset classes.
But it is something that the exchange is exploring.
- Interesting.
I don't want to ask maybe to you, Roger,
because obviously when we look at the perp market, right,
the crypto derivative market,
a big chunk of it is outside of the US, right?
Technically, legally, many of these US firms
are not allowed to trade on this big crypto derivative
platforms, even in the ETF space, right?
It was recently, this week, Hong Kong approved
not only the first Bitcoin spot ETF,
but also the first Ethereum spot ETF.
I think we all agree that the volumes and activity
we're going to see there is going to be a fraction
of what happened in the US.
But from your perspective, from an ETF perspective,
what do you think the impact of this could be,
of this Hong Kong approval, especially when you consider
the Asian activity in broader crypto derivative markets?
- Well, I think, again, the success of the spot Bitcoin
ETF in the US market is going to have a large number
of providers open their eyes and be able to look at
when I say providers, you know, ETF issuers
are going to be opening their eyes and looking at.
These are ways now, these are additional ways
where some of the other asset classes that we've had,
you know, underneath our umbrella in the public markets,
this is a faster growing asset class, right?
I mean, if you're in the asset management business
and you're earning advice fees for doing these things,
you're going to be naturally looking at
where business is growing and whether it's the ETFs
that are launching in Hong Kong or in the other jurisdiction
that we're likely to see across planet Earth,
it's a big tipping point for the industry in general.
The mainstream adoption of these really network economy
is what Bitcoin represents.
And, you know, we're going to be talking about Bitcoin,
but, you know, next year this time
you'll be talking about Ethereum
and you'll be talking about any other number of other projects
that might be able to be delivered,
whether it's in single asset ETFs or in multi-coin products.
And I think that's where we have a Franklin Templeton,
a future vision of how do we take this environment
where there's value and offer advice
along tried and true things such as portfolio diversification,
right, where is value inside of some of these network economies
that will accrue to holders of these assets?
Can we get them in the type of form
that delivers into where the assets are,
that the broker-dealer accounts have trillions of dollars
of assets in them?
And so if we can get a mechanism toward that access,
then I think we're in a whole new ballgame, quite frankly.
But how are you seeing the reaction of this market, right?
So let's say the 401(k) market alone
is a $6 trillion industry, right?
When you guys are pitching this product
to financial advisors, institutional investors,
what's their reaction so far?
'Cause obviously we hear a lot
that there's a cooling off period
before advice of the visors can deal with institutional investors.
- Clearly in the US market, the 401(k) is different
than somebody's, either at institutions or individuals,
an account, there's a lot more regulation
because of the fiduciary responsibilities
that a company and the operators of that 401(k) plan have.
I mean, we have seen, it's taken a long time
for a lot of different innovation to happen
in the 401(k) market specifically.
But, you know, again, everything, every journey starts
with one step and to the extent
that we actually have these network economies,
Bitcoin, Ethereum, others represented inside
of a delivery mechanism that fits inside of that,
then I think it's just a matter of time
where the education comes forward
and we see more and more adoption
in a lot of different places.
- One last point on this, you know,
what was interesting I found in the Hong Kong approval
is they were doing an in kind creation
and redemption mechanism.
And of course in the US, it's a in cash mechanism.
Were you surprised that Hong Kong took the step forward
to do it in kind?
And do you expect the future,
the if and when the ETF is gonna be happening,
is gonna be cash or in kind?
- I don't think it really surprised us,
particularly because as we've been in our journey
and digital assets now for about six or seven years,
but we came at it by looking at just,
how can we use blockchain technology
and operating inside of what we do
in asset management business?
We found a use case in the transfer agency responsibilities
we have, record keeping, I mean these blockchain networks
are massive record keeping systems, quite frankly.
And when we uncovered some of the efficiency gains
of using these network distributed ledger platforms
versus our proprietary single database providers,
it really gave us comfort that a lot of change
is gonna be coming and we needed to keep doubling down
and putting more resources.
And what we're finding is there's regulators outside of the US
that are far more friendly.
So it's not really surprising that Hong Kong
is gonna be taking another step forward
beyond what the US market is gonna be now.
- Very interesting.
If you wanna move into you talk about
like the market participants, right?
Let's talk about crypto for a second.
Right now when we look at crypto markets,
there's really two, three exchanges
that are the vast majority of the volumes on a daily basis.
From a consumer, from a personal perspective,
when you look at five years down the line,
do you believe we're gonna be in the same kind of market
where there's one or two players that dominate?
Will it be the same players?
Or do you think the landscape may change
from a centralized exchange perspective?
- Yeah, I think like the default view is,
yeah, we should see something like
some kind of like repetition of what we see
in traditional finance.
So there probably will be a few regional,
big regional players and maybe one or two global players,
just like we see, I know, derivative space currently
dominated by CME in your X, for example, globally.
So it would be kind of a default view
to expect to write here, but I'm kind of hopeful
that we'll see a bit more, yeah,
a bit more fractured market.
So quite a few more exchanges,
especially on DeFi side and a lot more competition.
That's kind of a hope for us as well.
And that's what we are kind of building towards as well.
- But when we add to that, if you think of what's happening
with the ETFs and the success that we spoke about earlier,
but do you think like, for example,
could there be more, say, people using the ETF
for access versus folk looking to trade
on centralized exchanges, right?
So that remains to be seen.
Certainly I think we're in very early days, right?
Already the ETFs, I think over like 30 billion or so,
easily, right, which is phenomenal.
But I think that we were only seeing
like a fraction of the participants in that market yet.
You don't have the wire houses fully there yet.
You don't have all the registered investment advisors there.
So that particular market could be huge.
It'd be interesting to see how that impacts
some of the centralized exchanges going forward.
But I would anticipate that there would be
perhaps some consolidation amongst the centralized exchanges, right?
- Because technically, if you argue
from a US retail investor right now, ironically,
maybe cheaper for me to go buy an ETF,
then go open an account on a centralized exchange
and trade along with the counterparty risk
and this and that and the fiat on and outfraps.
I mean, it's a bit, it's very ironic on that person.
At the end of the US side, right?
- Yeah, easy VC, which is our Bitcoin offering is free.
- Yeah, there you go.
- It's cheaper than free, right?
- I mean, even for you guys, it must be kind of a lost leader.
I mean, there's a cost as a business
to come in and offer to service for some time.
- It is.
- But the gather day, you have this eraser way, you have it in a way.
- Yeah, I mean, Franklin Temple then has been
in the asset management business
and I think we're celebrating our 76th year.
You know, we're in a business of trust.
We understand that intimately and to build that trust.
Once you gain that trust,
you can keep it for a long period of time
as long as you're doing right by customers.
And there's no doubt that where it currently stands
in the retail marketplace in the US,
you have the wire houses, the wealth management platforms
are doing their due diligence to select, you know,
who the limited number of providers might be.
They're allowing their platforms to be able
for you to purchase it.
It's, you know, self-directed.
They're not offering any discretionary advice.
That's the tipping point.
When there's more realization that these networks
are hugely powerful rails,
off of which the data economy is going to be moving,
going forward, it's that big picture of thematic story.
When there's more understanding about that,
there will be much more adoption
and we're likely to see, you know,
probably a lot higher price action quite frankly.
- And I think that it's also like a function of like,
like where you are.
Because certainly the ETF, you know,
you hear not your keys, not your crypto, right?
And if you have the ETF, you're really getting cash exposure
to, you know, the price of Bitcoin.
But I do anticipate that there's other economies,
for example, for other reasons
why people may actually want to hold the coin, right?
And you can't trade the ETF on weekends.
You know, we spoke about weekend trading before, right?
- Of course.
- But you also can't take that ETF
and transfer it to somebody else if you want to,
you know, exchange.
So I think that there's, there's,
there's are different like users.
And, you know, the user base may be in developed countries,
may get their exposure through a cash-based product.
But I think of other like, like countries
where there may be a better use case
for something like, like Bitcoin.
- But then you can argue the use case is different, right?
For somebody who's in Turkey, Nigeria,
and Argentina, they want to hedge against inflation
or whatever, even stablecoins, I would argue,
the purpose is different.
But there's a big chunk of the market
who are buying my mom in Montreal, Canada,
when she wants to buy Bitcoin,
'cause you know, she wants to understand what I do in life.
I think that for her, there's a perfect use case
where ETF could be better than going on a centralized exchange,
understanding what a Ethereum network is
or a Tron network is and so on and so forth, right?
- Yeah, 100%.
- And that market is quite big.
Actually, it brings a good point
because I'll get your point of view on this, if Genny,
what I find very interesting right now in markets in crypto
is that there's a massive disconnect, right?
I mean, for example, the rate of borrow,
if you say you want to trade on crypto exchanges,
you want to trade perpetual swaps,
the borrow of USDT, for example, is extremely high.
And during last bull market last month,
I mean, retail was paying over 50, 100% in some cases.
But if you go into traditional space,
you can obviously the cost of borrowing dollars
is significantly lower.
What do you think is going to have to have this,
like, discrepancy change and from a trading perspective,
what do you think is going to take for this arbitrage
to disappear in a way?
- I mean, the main challenge is there are very few players
who are present, who are vegetarian on CME
and on Binance and in DeFi,
and we have the funding rates are pretty different on all three.
There are very few players, like us,
is one of those few players who are actually operating
in every event, you ultimately need to make a choice
where to deploy a capital.
And as we, as crypto grows and as we see more players
entering the space, entering, I know Binance is closed
for a lot of US pro-playing, for example, at the moment.
So it already makes it a lot harder to close this funding gap.
So we'll see, it will take a lot more market participants
entering to put those rates, normalize those rates
between different parts of the ecosystem.
- And where you see those market participants come from,
actually, when you look at the global landscape
and you look at the next couple of years,
how do you see this market participant change,
especially where people are coming from?
- It's a big function of,
to big degree it's a function of regulators as well.
So I think the market participants coming from jurisdictions
with more liberal regulators, yeah,
it will be basically the first wave.
Once US regulators become a bit more liberal in US
and we'll see how, I don't know, elections this year go,
for example, I think that should unlock a lot more, actually.
'Cause I would argue, in a certain extent,
tomorrow morning, you're launching a brand new crypto company.
No disrespect, but I think you'd be a bit of an idiot
to do this in the US, right?
There's so many jurisdictions now where you have
the regulatory comfort, the clarity and so on and so forth,
and the flexibility to trade the exchanges you want.
I just find it's very interesting,
the dynamic we're seeing on that perspective.
For products like ETF, it's a no-brainer for the CME,
of course, it is what it is, but on the trading side,
I think there's massive disadvantage
if you're set up in the US, actually.
No, it is, yeah, and we've seen a lot of competitors,
basically rearranging their operations
after the latest, like, Biden's action, for example, yeah.
So, let me talk about the future as well, about DeFi, right?
We talked about it in a second, a couple of minutes ago,
we talked about value creation, about the new economy.
When you see the future of DeFi, let's say in five years,
we have this conference in 2029 here in Dubai.
How do you see the world of DeFi would have evolved by then?
And how do you think it would have competed
with the centralized exchanges,
as well as traditional market participants?
- It's a function of two things.
So first, whether tech will work,
tech will scale effectively
for those decentralized platforms, like--
- A DEX?
- For DEXs, yeah, for DEXs, yeah.
So, I don't know, you see the IDX before, for example,
now, which is much more fully decentralized
compared to anyone else.
- Yeah, good, but we need to battle test it.
We need to see how much throughput it can handle.
We need to see, yeah, if it can even do a fraction
of what CME can handle, for example,
on the throughput side of things.
And the second factor is, again, regulation.
We see a lot of hostile regulations in general
across the world, like not all the countries,
but a lot of key countries are pretty hostile,
especially when it comes to self custody, for example.
And, yeah, if you cannot self custody,
it basically kills the whole point behind DEXs,
like then, yeah, then we stick with violence
and CME and Coinbase, yeah.
- Yeah, it doesn't work.
That's why it's gonna be interesting,
see what happens in the US on that side.
How do you think DeFi could affect your business?
Let's go on an exchange side.
How do you guys looking at the potential risk,
not risk, let's say, competition of DeFi down the line?
- Yeah, and a great question.
I think when you look at just the crypto space, right,
it's relatively new, I mean, Bitcoin's only been around
for about 16 years or so, right?
So a lot of these platforms, there's a lot of them, right?
But they're not time tested, you know, reliability,
you know, it could still be an issue, right?
Trust may be an issue.
And I think in order to get, you know,
tried by institutions to adapt some of these protocols,
some of those factors need to be there.
And I also think that you need, say, you know,
the point that you made earlier,
that regulatory clarity, you know, needs to be there, right?
And, you know, when you think of, you know,
something like Bitcoin, which is, you know, global, right?
And grew up almost by word of mouth initially, right?
On the regulatory front, I kind of feel that we need,
we also need to be global, right?
Where I think that, you know, the regulators need to get
together globally so that you don't have, say,
this regulatory arbitrage, right?
- I actually feel pretty good about,
I mean, I know there's a lot of pessimism about regulators
and, you know, being a little overbearing and the like,
but, you know, for sure, I think the focus on the regulators,
at least our communications with regulators,
and we've been shepherding several products
through the US regulators and the Luxembourg regulators,
what you find is that the focus has been on the asset
themselves, what is Bitcoin?
What are cryptocurrencies?
What do they do?
But after some time and education and collaboration,
beginning to understand what the networks
are capable of doing and how they can be an improvement
over the existing infrastructure,
I think you're gonna see in the next couple of years
a bigger realization about how the regulators can begin
to do their job easier because a lot of this activity
is riding on these public blockchain utilities,
quite frankly.
I mean, several years ago, when we started our,
having conversations with the SEC about our project,
Benji, our tokenized money fund project,
which is available in the US and we hope soon globally,
the conversations that we were having with them was,
look, if these transaction records take place
on these public blockchains, with the right tool sets,
and we know the SEC has the right surveillance tool sets,
with the right tool sets and people,
they can observe the movement of all these activities
a lot easier and so it benefits them as a stakeholder,
there's more efficiencies for the shareholders
of the product so they can earn more capital return,
it's easier and cheaper for the asset manager operate as well.
So I'm actually a lot more positive about that,
maybe because, you know, I'm now in my,
practically my 50th conversation with the SEC about projects
and I see the changing nature of their approach of,
let's understand what these technologies deliver for us
rather than focusing on the cryptocurrency itself
and the volatility of it.
- And I think that's interesting because when you talk,
let's say where we're in Dubai right now,
here at the Barra, the crypto regulator,
they regulate the activity, they actually don't regulate the assets,
which I think is a smart way because then your asset manager,
you're a broker dealer and that's how they look at it.
And by the way, every licensed firm here,
there's every weekly reporting of your wallet addresses
and of course the regulators are running
these on-chain analytics on the back-hander,
so they have obviously very good visibility.
So it's way more secure, I would argue,
from a risk management perspective,
than the old-school filing schedules that we do on the SEC.
- And let's be clear, the regulators are in communication
with each other, right?
It is a community of securities
and exchange-related regulators across the planet.
And if one of them is giving blessing,
it helps to that when you're having that conversation
with another one.
- Yeah, which is hopefully a good thing, you know?
But also, you mentioned about the,
for Tratify firms in the institutional setup, right?
I mean, I'd say while I was preparing for this panel,
I was pleasantly surprised to see that Franklin Templeton
offers like these staking services,
your guys are on various nodes.
How was it to try to bring crypto
within a 75-year-old Franklin Templeton organization
where there's obviously a lot of legacy,
and frankly, I'm sure, legacy mindset as well,
in some instances?
- Yeah, well, I think it helps if you have a partner
right at the top of the firm.
- Yeah.
- So Jenny Johnson, the CEO of Franklin Templeton,
is a risk taker.
- Yeah.
- And she understands the nature.
She spent a lot of years running the operations
of Franklin Templeton by and large,
and so she began to understand the technologies
probably far more than some other industry leaders have been.
So that's key right there.
They have a lot of access right at the top
with a belief system there.
And then I think the other component is
you just have to have a spirit of R&D, right?
You have to try things in order to get outcomes
by and large.
Not enough of that happens.
I think in the asset management business,
everybody looks at each other.
What did you do?
Oh, you raised money this way.
I could do that too.
But you have to be stepping forward.
And it's an entirely new community and user base
that Franklin Templeton is excited to engage in.
A couple of weeks ago when the spot Bitcoin ETFs came out,
we changed our corporate logo to include the laser eyes
on Franklin. - Yeah, I remember that.
- It was like five million views globally
for doing that, right?
That's saying that there's a different community
of engagement that recognizes that these blockchain environments
are creating new types of assets.
I've always had the idea that if you can expand
the opportunity set for your clients,
you might have an opportunity to raise
that efficient frontier.
Rather than just only increasing the risk,
you might be able to access more outcomes.
And I think that's kind of the vision that we have.
- It's very interesting actually how the top
leadership matters.
I mean, even some of your peers,
like the look at Vanguard, for example.
When the top is not bought in, forget about the rest.
I wanna see one guy's one quick question
before we move to the fire round question,
it's about talent, right?
So it's very good you guys doing the laser eyes
and so on and so forth.
You know, I'm a university professor,
I've been teaching cryptos in 2015, right?
And every year I've many of my students
want to join the crypto industry.
And they always ask me two questions,
they're like, oh, should I go over for a crypto firm?
Should I work for a tratify firm
who's getting into crypto?
How do you convince somebody?
Actually, let me start from your side.
When you're getting talent, first of all,
where are you getting talent?
And then I wanna hear from your side, guys,
on a tratify side, how are you able to convince people
to work for your organizations
when they have the choice to go work for this crypto firm,
to the crypto.
I've been here to start from you.
- Yeah, I think the key thing we learned,
because we're operating for seven years now.
The key thing we learned is it's much more important
to get people who are bought in into the mission of crypto,
bought into the whole ecosystem and not just here
because I mess around, not just here,
because I don't do this, because it's a bull market
and I can make it with money.
And we've been traditionally growing slowly,
but steadily, we've been basically adding people
every year since 2018, even in the bare markets.
And it's been quite important for us
to get the right alignment, the right culture.
It's really hard because we are competing with the HFTs,
we are competing with syntax,
we are competing with crypto protocols, it's tough.
- So what are you looking for?
When you're hiring somebody,
what is the one thing you're looking for?
- Basic culture alignment, which in our case is,
yeah, right work ethic, crazy work in ours.
- Yeah, you need to be a bit crazy to work in crypto, huh?
- This 24/7 aspect is real.
I mean, not 24, but like, yeah, seven days a week
I think that's real, so we have to look at it.
- What have you found works best to hire people
to come on?
- Well, I think not enough of this is done.
Giving permission to some of your own employees to explore.
I mean, when you invest over decades
and you create wisdom among your staff
and you give them some latitude
to begin to apply that wisdom somewhere new,
it's super engaging for them, right?
They wanna be with you for the long term
and you gain from all of that industry wisdom
that's come across different cycles
and seeing things, giving people inside
of your own organization more ability,
more permissions to do things has been really important.
Some of our very best, most talented employees
aren't ones that we've had to go recruit from outside,
it's just taking people that have been long standing,
great employees who see a vision for something new
and are gonna apply all their experience toward it.
- And often there could be some of the most junior employees
as well, which is interesting.
On your start, Giovanni, how are you guys getting able
to hire people when technically somebody
could go to crypto exchange?
- Yeah, so I mean, CME is a 180 year old institution, right?
But we've been innovating for those 180 years, right?
When you look at the crypto space itself,
I mean, we've been in this space now since 2015,
initially launching reference rates on big point
and providing price transparency.
We now have reference rates in real-time indices
covering over 20 different coins and tokens.
Obviously we have futures and options on futures
on both big point and ether.
But like Roger mentioned, in terms of talent,
some of our talent, we're a relatively small organization.
I think we've got maybe 3,500 employees
covering six different asset classes, seven,
if you count crypto.
And we too also promote, say, from within
and trained for from within.
But I recently added somebody on my team
and I could share with you that we had,
for that one position, like almost immediately,
like over a thousand applications for that one one.
- Here we go.
- And those applications came,
not just they came from some trad buy participants,
but we also saw folks that are working, say,
in the crypto space and are looking, say,
to explore opportunities within a trad buy firm
that's expanding, say, in this area.
So it's been super exciting.
But what I find about this space, though,
is that it's just very collaborative.
I find that we compete,
but we're also all interested in really growing this space.
- It's just the beauty of it.
I think the crypto industry on that one.
So guys, we have about two minutes left.
My bell is with me, my best friend.
Always with our song, guys, I'm gonna ask you
quick questions and I need one or two word answers, right?
And the bell is here to keep us honest.
I'm gonna start with you, Giovanni,
and we're gonna move on, Roger, and then again.
You guys are ready?
- Unscripted.
- Here we go.
What is the one development in crypto
you are the most excited for the next five years?
- I think tokenization.
- At the tokenization.
- Tokenization, Roger.
- Yeah, tokenization.
- Really, RWA, interesting.
What is the one that development in crypto
you're the most excited about?
- Dexxas.
Dexxas.
- Dexxas, essentially, I find it.
I'm starting from you, Revgeny.
What is the one biggest risk we face
as a crypto ecosystem today?
- Regulation.
- Regulation, interesting.
Roger, what's the biggest risk we're facing?
We should all be worried in the room.
- I think it's education.
- Interesting.
- Yeah, lack of regulation.
- Regulation as well.
I'm starting from you on this side, Giovanni.
If you could hold one cryptocurrency for the next 10 years,
you're not allowed to sell it.
What do you hold?
- I like ether.
- Etherium is a great project.
- I'll go with the spice one.
Doge.
- Doge?
- There you go.
My God.
This is a tricky one.
I'm starting with you, Evgeny.
If you could launch a new crypto business,
a new crypto startup,
and you can choose any crypto CEO,
entrepreneur, as your co-founder,
who would you choose?
- Oh, my God.
Any CEO, co-founder.
- Any CEO, entrepreneur, and a crypto space.
- I'll go with, yeah.
You guys are gonna have him as a speaker as well,
I think a bit later.
Tristan from Backpack.
- Tristan from Backpack, interesting.
Yeah, firm was actually based here.
There you go, Roger.
- I'm not gonna,
I have too many friends in the industry
to vote on that one.
(laughs)
- Same answer.
- I have to go with my current boss, Tim McQuar.
- Here we go.
- It's been great for me.
- Very, very diplomatically correct here.
This isn't tricky one.
I'm starting from you, Evgeny.
You could have lunch with Gary Gensler.
You're having lunch with Gary Gensler.
What is the one thing you tell him?
- Oh.
(laughs)
Yeah, I'll just ask him,
when they start in speculations for Bitcoin, yeah.
- That's crazy.
- That's ridiculous.
- Roger where you tell Gary Gensler for lunch.
- No, I'm not going that one either.
Giovanni.
- I might have to say goodbye.
(laughs)
- Quick one, two more left.
I'm starting from you.
If you're not in the crypto industry,
what would you be doing?
- Oh boy, innovating.
- Innovation.
Coaching basketball.
- Coaching basketball.
Here we go.
After you're gone married.
- You know, gaming, I guess?
- Gaming.
Here we go.
The Warhammer fan comes out.
And guys, the last question to finish off this panel,
the traditional question,
whoever goes on stage with me,
I'm starting from you, Evgeny.
If you could have lunch or dinner,
one percent, dead or alive.
You could have lunch or dinner with one percent,
dead or alive.
Who would you have lunch or dinner with?
- Oh, dammit.
(laughs)
- Really hard one.
Can I go last and think of it more?
- Roger.
Abraham Lincoln.
- Abraham Lincoln, here we go.
We're patriotic.
- For me, I'd have to say my father.
- Your father.
- Oh my God.
- What a great way to end this panel, guys.
Thank you very much.
It was a great seeing you.
A big counter-boss for the panel.
Thank you very much, guys.
Enjoy the rest of the day.
(audience applauds)
- Thank you very much to our panel.
And on we are slated.
On we hold up just a second.
I'll let the rest of you go, please.
Giovanni, thank you so much for joining us.
God, see you.
Roger, thank you so much.
You good?
You're welcome.
- Thank you.
- And I have to admit, ladies and gentlemen,
I am taking a moment to pause
before I let Henri Arslanian go.
Not only so, I can like flash his book around.
Are you going to be available for signatures?
- Yeah, I'm here.
I'm here early today, today, tomorrow.
- Great.
And during the session, I got a phone call
from the Dubai regulator at the Dubai regulator.
He says, "Hey Andrew, don't forget to mention
"that Henri's $150 million market neutral crypto hedge fund
"has been approved by V-A-R-A."
And they said, "Don't forget to mention,
"so Henri, you know, didn't want to miss that out
"'cause we are here in Dubai."
- Awesome.
- Amazing.
Thank you.
- Thank you very much.
(upbeat music)